Guide to the Incunabula Collection at Stanford University, 1467-1500
Department of Special Collections
- Durand, Guillaume, ca. 1230-1296. Incipit Racionale diuinorum officiorum.[Basel: Berthold Ruppel and Michael Wenssler, not after 1477]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1477 .D8 f; [414] p. (p. [1]-[2], [414] blank); 41 cm.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: capitals, initial-strokes, and foliation (with errors) in red. Title in ms. on p. [5]: Rationale diuinorum Gvilhelmi Durandi F.V.D. Episcopi Mimatensis. Binder: monastic bindery of Kloster St. Veit (stamp "vitus" on upper cover; cf. Goldschmidt). Binding: stamped pigskin over boards; remains of 2 fore-edge clasps; trace of chaining staple on top edge of back cover; edges blue. Provenance: Andreae Buchneri (booklabel); ms. marginalia. Imperfect: lacks 8 leaves: [a1], [h1], [k4], [n6], [q4-7]; [a4] mutilated with loss of text; some leaves mended; quire [q] slit at gutter.
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. La commedia.[Venice]: Vindelinus de Spira, 1477., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1477 .D36 f; [752] p.; 34 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 248 (IB.20577). Goff (rev.), D-27. GW 7964. Hain-Copinger 5942. ISTC, id00027000. Mambelli, G. Ed. Dantesche, 7.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: Untouched. Binding: gilt red morocco, panelled spine, with elephant crest on blue morocco inlay; in slip case by Jas. Macdonald Co., N.Y. On spine: Dante: Spiera: 1477. Imperfect: lacks first 16 leaves containing Vita by Boccaccio. Provenance: Roderick Terry (bookplate); Giorgio Fanan (bookplate); scant ms. marginalia.
- [Decisiones Rotae Romanae]. In ciuitate Maguntina: Imp[re]ssorie artis inue[n]trice elimatriceq[ue] p[ri]ma Petrus Schoyffer de Gernssheym ..., anno D[omi]ni 1477 pridie Nonis Ianuariis [4 Jan.], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1477 .D43 f; [580] p.; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 33 (IB.214). Goff (rev.), D-108. GW 8201. Hain 6047. ISTC (RLIN), id00108000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding order: 2 blank leaves; Decisiones antiquae; index to Decisiones antiquae; index to Decisiones novae; Decisiones novae (287 leaves total). Imperfect: colophon (at end of Decisiones novae) removed and replaced by ms. copy within red rules with red initial stroke and red printer's mark; lacks 3? blank leaves. Binding: calf, rebacked; title labels on panelled spine. Binder's title: Decisiones dom. de Rota. Schffer Magunt. 1477. Provenance: The William Blades Library, St. Bride Foundation (ink-stamp); ms. marginalia and underscoring.
- Theophylactus, of Ochrida, Archbishop of Ochrida, ca. 1050-ca. 1108. In prima Pauli ad Romanos epistola Athanasii prologus. Rome impressum: Per ingeniosum uirum Magistrum Vdalricum Gallum alias Han Alamanum ex Ingelstat ciue[m] Wienensem ..., anno incarnationis Dominice 1477 die uero 25 mensis Ianuarii ..., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1477 .T46 f; [556] p.; 34 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., IV, p. 25 (IB.17343). Goff (rev.), T-15. Hain 1902. ISTC (RLIN), it00156000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials in gold, white, red, blue and green, one in red only; floral border with coat of arms in gold, white, red, blue and green on [a2r]. Binding: blind-stamped morocco over boards, somewhat repaired; stumps of clasps. Provenance: Sio[n]is Civit Casteili Minor. Obser. (ink-stamp); ms. marginalia and underscoring.
- Vincent, of Beauvais, d. 1264. Speculu[m] doctri[n]ale.[Strassburg: The R-Printer (Adolph Rusch), not before 1477], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1477 .V56 ff; [808] p.; 51 cm.
  References: Copinger 6242. Goff (rev.), V-278. ISTC (RLIN), iv00278000. Polain 3938.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Initials, initial strokes, and paragraph marks in red; scant underscoring in red and blue. Imperfect: lacks pp. [1]-[2] (blanks) and [301]-[304]. Binding: blind-stamped full vellum over wooden boards; guards; leather tabs; clasps; in case. Binder's title: [Vin?]centii Bel[vac.?] [S?]peculum doctrina[le?]; leather label affixed to upper cover: Speculum doctrinale [?]. Provenance: Ewald Flgel Library (booklabel and ink-stamp); Oswald Weigel Antiquariat Auctions-Institut, Leipzig ... (ink-stamp).
- Jacobus, de Voragine, ca. 1229-1298. Incipit prologus sup[er] lege[n]das sanctorum quas co[m]pilauit Frater Iacobus Ianuensis natione de Ordine Fratrum Predicatorum. Impressi in opido Vlm: Per Iohanne[m] Zainer, [not after 1478]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1478 .J23 f; [836] p. (1st 2 p. blank); 30 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 529 (IB.9237). Copinger 6390. Goff (rev.), J-91. ISTC (RLIN), ij00091000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: leaves [a1] (blank), [c5], [c6] and [S**] (blank) lacking; printing errors on [i6] and [k5] with loss of text. Binding: blind stamped leather over boards; ms. title label on spine; clasps. Spine title: Legenda in or[dine] festa sanctoru[m] seu Historia Lompardica ... Provenance: extensive ms provenance in late medieval hands; Fab. Salicetus (signature); M. Wolfgangi Graber Petri (signature); Joannes Niger (signature); ms. marginalia, emendations and underscoring.
- Plutarch. Virorum illustrium uitae / ex Plutarcho Graeco in Latinum uersae solertiq[ue] cura emendatae foeliciter expliciu[n]t.[Venice]: Per Nicolaum Ienson Gallicum Venetiis i[m]pressae, M.cccc.lxxviii die ii Ianuarii [2 January 1478], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1478 .P58 f; 2 v. ([468] p.; [452] p.); 41 cm.
  Includes registers at end of each volume.
  References: BM 15th cent. V, p. 178 (IC.19711). Goff (rev.), P-832. Hain-Copinger 13127. ISTC (RLIN), ip00832000b.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: paragraph marks in red. Imperfect: lacks 10, the register for v.2. Binding: blind- stamped leather. Binder's title: Plvtarco. Provenance: Philip C. Duschnes (bookseller's label); extensive ms. marginalia throughout; fists; partially foliated in ms.; ms. index of names on a1v; some guide letters supplied in ms.
- Perotti, Niccol, 1430-1480. Nicolai Perotti pontificis Sypontini ad Pyrrhum Perottum nepotem ex fratre suauissimum Rudimenta grammatices. Venetiis: [s.n.], 1478 tertio Idus Martii [13 March], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1478 .P365; [220] p. (first and last p. blank); 28 cm.
  References: Butler, P. Check list of 15th cent. books, 839. Goff (rev.) P-309. Hain 12657. IGI 7444. ISTC (RLIN), ip00309000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials in blue or red added consistently through h4, sporadically thereafter. Binding: gilt calf, panelled spine, gilt turn-ins; marbled endpapers; blank leaves bound in at beginning and end. On spine: Nic. Perotti Grammatic. Venetiis 1478. Ms. marginalia and emendations.
- Sacro Bosco, Joannes de, fl. 1230. Iohannis de Sacrobusto, Anglici, uiri clarissimi, Spera mundi feliciter incipit. Impressa Venetijs: Per Franciscu[m] Renner de Hailbrun, 1478., Call No. Barchas Collection KA1478 .S2; [96] p.: diagrams (woodcuts); 21 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 195 (IA.19869). Goff (rev.) J-402. Hain-Copinger 14108*. ISTC, ij00402000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Binding: gilt mottled calf. Provenance: Henry de Cessole (signature); ms. marginalia.
- Eusebius, of Caesarea, Bishop of Caesarea, ca. 260-ca. 340. Incipit liber primus hystorie ecclesiastice.[Mantua: Johann Schall, not before 15 July 1479], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1479 .E94 f; [344] p.; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VII, p. 933 (IB.30664). Goff (rev.), E-127. GW 9437. Hain-Copinger, 6711. ISTC, ie00127000. Polain 1428.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): untouched; foliation added in pencil. Imperfect: lacks final blank leaf. Binder: D[ouglas] C[ockerell], 1905 (stamped on lower turn-in). Binding: red morocco, with tooling in leaf dot pattern on covers; gold tooled turn-ins; raised bands. Binder's title: Eusebii Historia ecclesiastica. Provenance: C.H. St. John Hornby (bookplate); Clifford Rattey (bookplate).
- Nicholas, of Lyra, ca. 1270-1349. Incipiunt Moralia super totam Bibliam Fratris Nicolai de Lira de Ordine Fratru[m] Minorum sacre theologie venerabilis doctoris.[Strasbourg: Georg Husner, ca. 1479], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1479 .N49 f; [552] p. (1st 2 p. and last 2 p. blank); 42 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 86 (IC.1057). Goff (rev.), N-112. Hain 10372. ISTC (RLIN), in00112000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: capitals in red, blue, or red and blue, some with white as well; paragraph marks, initial strokes and underscoring in red. Imperfect: final blank missing. Binding: calf over boards; rebacked; remnants of clasps. Provenance: Gerald Poynton Mander (booklabel); ms. index on 1st blank leaf; ms. headlines and foliation.
- Eusebius, of Caesarea, Bishop of Caesarea, ca. 260-ca. 340. Eusebius Pamphili de euangelica praeparatione / a Georgio Trapezuntio traductus.[Treviso]: Michael Manzolinus Parmensis exactissima impressit diligentia Taruisii, anno humanitatis Christi M.cccclxxx pridie Idus Ianuarias [12 Jan. 1480], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1480 .E9; [216] p.; 29 cm.
  References: BMC 15th cent., VI, p. 888 (IB.28358). Goff (rev.), E-121. GW 9443. Hain-Copinger, 6702. ISTC, ie00121000. Pellechet, 4644. Polain 1432. Stillwell E.94.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): untouched. Imperfect: lacks first and final blanks, a1 and p8. Binding: vellum, red-speckled edges. Binder's title: Eusebius. Provenance: Giorgio di Veroli (booklabel); scant ms. marginalia.
- Nicholas, of Lyra, ca. 1270-1349. Postilla super Actus Apostolorum Fratris Nicolai de Lyra Ordinis Mino[rum] incipit. Impressum Mantue: P[er] Paulum Johannis de Butschbach ..., anno D[omi]ni M.CCCC.Lxxx die v[er]o xxx. Marcij [30 March 1480], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1480 .N52; [232] p. (first 2 and last 2 blank); 27 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VII, p. 932 (IB.30647). Goff (rev.), N-115. Hain-Copinger 10395. ISTC (RLIN), in00115000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Imperfect: lacks A1, g8 (both blanks) as called for in BM 15th cent., VII, p. 932. Binding: vellum spine, paper boards. Provenance: shelf label on spine reads II E H10395 Lyra Mantua 1480.
- Bible. O.T. Psalms. Greek. Septuagint. 1481. Impressum Mediolani: [Bonus Accursius], anno Mcccc.Lxxxi die xx. Septembris [20 September 1481], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .B53 f; [364] p. (first and last p. blank); 29 cm.
  Includes the Magnificat and Benedictus Dominus.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 757 (IB.26564b). Darlow Moule, 4590. Goff (rev.), P-1035. Hain-Copinger 13454. ISTC (RLIN), ip01035000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Variant: last line on g7r reads: hola-, as in BM 15th cent., VI, p. 757 (IB.26564b), but the "p" is present in September in colophon, as in IB.26564a. Rubrication: untouched. Binding: brown morocco, gilt panels with gilt devices on upper and lower covers; gilt paneled spine, gilt turn-ins; all edges gilt; in case (33 cm.) with spine title: Psalterium Graeco-Latinum. Binder's title: Psalterium Gr. et Lat. Mediolani 1481. Binder: R. De Coverly (stamp). Provenance: Wm. Crocker deposit (inscription); bequest of Mr. and Mrs. William H. Crocker (bookplate); 302 (shelf label).
- Colonne, Guido delle, 13th cent. Incomincia il prolago sopra la Historia di Troia Nella inchlita citta di Venexia: Impressa per Antonio de Allexandria della Paglia, Bartholomeo da Fossombrono dela Marcha Marchesino di Sauioni Milanese, negli anni della incarnatione 1481., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .C66; [216] p.; 28 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 297 (IB.21297). Goff (rev.), C-782. GW 7242. Hain-Copinger 5523. ISTC (RLIN), ic00782000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: lacks 1st blank leaf. Binding: full vellum. Binder's title (red capitals): Guido de Columna. Historia di Troia. Venexia. 1481. Provenance: ms. marginalia and underscoring.
- Durand, Guillaume, ca. 1230-1296. Incipit rat[i]onale diuino[rum] officio[rum][Nuremberg]: ... industria Anthonij Koburger Nure[m]berge exaratu[m] ..., 1481 viij ydus Noue[m]bris [6 Nov.], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .D8 f; [1], cxcvij leaves; 33 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 421 (IB.7235). Goff (rev.) D-425. GW 9123. Hain 6485. ISTC, id00425000. Stillwell D349. Pellechet 4504. Proctor 2009.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: capitals, initial-strokes and paragraph marks added in red on most leaves. Binding: white pigskin, blind tooled (1984). Binder: Don Etherington (signed dated conservation treatment form laid in). Provenance: Ewald Flgel (booklabel).
- Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321. Comento di Christophoro Landino fiorentino sopra La comedia di Danthe Alighieri poeta fiorentino. Impresso in Firenze: Per Nicholo di Lorenzo della Magna, a di XXX. dagosto. M.CCCC.LXXXI [30 August 1481]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .D36 f; [744] p.: ill.; 28 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., VI, p. 628 (IC.27095b). Goff (rev.), D-29. GW 7966. Hain-Copinger 5496. ISTC (RLIN), id000029000b.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Imperfect: contains the illustrations for the first two cantos only, both of which appear printed directly on pages of text; lacks a1, 2L11-2L12 (blanks). Binding: full red leather, gilt panels with gilt designs at each corner on upper and lower covers; guards; in box. Binder's title: Coment. Danthe. Provenance: Giorgio Fanan (bookplate); Clifton Waller Barrett (armorial bookplate); Louis Thompson Rowe of XV Hammersmith Terrace, W. (booklabel); two armorial bookplates bearing the motto Vernon semper viret; unidentified armorial crest; foliated in ms., with errors.
- Nicholas, of Lyra, ca. 1270-1349. Prologus primus venerabilis Fratris Nicolai de Lira in Testamentum Vetus de recomme[n]dat[i]one sacre scripture in generali incipit.[Nuremberg]: Et industria impensisq[ue] Anthonij Koburger incole Nurnbergen[sis] q[uam] diligenter exaratis, atq[ue] 22 mensis Ianuarij anno salutis 1481 co[n]summatis., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .N5 f; 2 v.: ill.; 42 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 419 (IC.7206). Goff (rev.), N-135. Hain-Copinger 10369. ISTC (RLIN), in00135000. Sajo, Geza. Catalogus incunabulorum Hungariae, 2406.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: 1st 267 leaves of v. 2 only, preceded by a blank leaf with ms. contents on verso, consisting of commentaries on Proverbs to 2 Maccabees. Last leaf is ms. reproduction of original leaf. Leaf 227 is variant described by Catalogus incunabulorum quae in bibliothecis publicis Hungariae asservantur under 2406 as leaf 226. Cf. BM 15th cent., v. 2, p. 419 for foliation. Rubrication: headings, initials, initial strokes, paragraph marks and underscoring in red or red and white; woodcuts outlined and colored in red. Binding: blind-stamped leather over boards; ms. title label on upper cover. Binder's title: Comment. in S. Scrip. Nicolai de Lyra. Provenance: Conventus Rezensis (inscription); ms. marginalia.
- Platina, 1421-1481. Platine historici liber de vita Christi ac pontificum omniu[m]: qui hactenus ducenti [et] vigintiduo fuere.[Nuremberg]: Accurate castigatu[m] ac impe[n]sa Antonij Koburger Nurenberge impressu[m], iij Idus Augusti consummatum, anno salutis xpiane [i.e. Christiane] M.cccclxxxj [11 Aug. 1481], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .P47 f; [256] p.; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 420 (IB.7224). Goff (rev.), P-769. Hain-Copinger, 13047. ISTC, ip00769000. Polain 3187.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: capitals and initial strokes added in red. Binding: full calf, with [German?] coat of arms stamped in gilt on covers. Binder's title: Platina. De vitis pontific.
- Pius II, Pope, 1405-1464. Epistolae familiares[Nuremberg]: Impensis Antonij Koburger Nure[m]berge imp[re]sse finiu[n]t, xvj. K[a]l[endi]s Octobris anno salutis Christiane [et]c[etera] M.cccc.lxxxj [16 September 1481], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .P397; [492] p.; 27 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 421 (IB.7232). Goff (rev.), P-717. Hain-Copinger 151. ISTC (RLIN), ip00717000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initial large capital illustrated in blue, green, red, and gilt, with blue, red, and gilt floral borders. Initials and paragraph marks in red and blue; initial strokes in red; Binding error: pp. [481]-[492] as called for by BM 15th cent., II, p. 421 (IB7232) misbound preceding p. [1]. Binding: full brown morocco, gilt arabesque turn-ins, marbled endpapers, gilt edges. Binder: Chambolle-Duru (stamp). Binder's title: Enee Silvii Epistolae 1481. Provenance: Wm. Crocker deposit (inscription); bequest of Mr. and Mrs. William H. Crocker (bookplate).
- Rolevinck, Werner, 1425-1502. Fasciculus temporum.[Venice]: Impressusq[ue] impensa [et] arte mira Erhardi Rodolt de Augusta, 1481. 12. calen[darum] Ian[uarii] [21 Dec. 1481], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .R65 f; [8], 64 leaves: ill. (woodcuts); 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent. V, p. 285 (IB.20508). Goff (rev.), R-264. Hain-Copinger 6928. ISTC (RLIN), ir00264000b.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Binding: full vellum; in box. Binder's title: Fascic. Tempo. Provenance: Coll. Pr[ep?] Fid. (ink-stamp).
- Torquemada, Juan de, 1388-1468. Qu[a]estiones Eua[n]gelioru[m] tam de tempore q[uam] de sanct[is] / collect[a]e per R.D. Iohanne[m] de Turre Cremata ep[iscopu]m Sabinen[sis] Sanct[a]e Rhoman[a]e Ecclesi[a]e cardinalem Sancti Sixti.[Basel: Johann Amerbach, not after 28 Sept. 1481], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .T6 f; [700] p.; 30 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 747 (IB.37283). Goff (rev.), T-553. Hain-Copinger 15714. ISTC (RLIN), it00553000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: Initials in red or blue (some in red and blue); initial strokes, paragraph marks, underscoring in red. Signed by rubricator: anno [etc.?] 1482. Imperfect: lacks 1st blank leaf. Binding: blind-stamped leather over boards; remnants of clasps; title label on upper cover. In case, with spine title: Questiones Evangeliorum. Basel. 1484. Provenance: ms marginalia.
- Tractatus quidam de Turcis Incipit tractatus quida[m] de Turcis p[ro]ut ad p[rae]sens ecclesia sancta ab eis affligit[ur] / collectus dilige[n]ti discussione scripturaru[m] a q[ui]busda[m] fratrib[us] ordinis p[rae]dicatorum q[ui] etia[m] d[e] trib[us] p[ri]ncipaliter tractat. Incipit tractatus quidam de Turcis. Impressus ... Nure[m]berge: Per Conradum Zeninger, ... 1481., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481 .T7; [48] p.; 20 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 460 (IA.7939). Goff (rev.) T-503. Hain 15681. Frankfurt Inkunabelkatalog 2847. ISTC, it00503000. Oates 1077.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: brown wrappers. Imperfect: lacks p. [1]-[2] and p. [33]-[48].
- Vincent, of Beauvais, d. 1264. Incipit Speculum naturale Vincentii Beluacensis Fratris Ordinis Predicatoru[m].[Strasbourg: Printer of the Legenda aurea, ca. 1481], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1481.V59 f; 2 v.; 46 cm.
  References: Copinger 6257. Goff (rev.), V-293. ISTC (RLIN), iv00293000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: large initials, many with floral borders, in red, blue, green, yellow; other initials, initial strokes, and paragraph marks in red or blue. Imperfect: all blank leaves lacking. Binding: blind-stamped leather over boards; clasps. Binder's title: Speculu[m] Naturale. Provenance: Mon[aste]rij B. Virg. in Bildhausen (inscription); H. St. Steinacher (signature); Oswald Weigel ... Leipzig (bookseller's stamp); Ewald Flgel library (label).
- Persius. Auli Flacci Persii poetae Satirarum opus. Venetiis: Per Baptistam de Tortis, 1482 die vi Decembris [6 Dec.], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1482. P37 f; [52] p. (first and last p. blank); 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 322 (IB.21338). Goff (rev.), P-344. Hain-Copinger, 12721. ISTC, ip00344000. Stillwell, P-304.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: decorated initial (a2) in purple, red, green, yellow, white and gold ink; smaller capitals, initial strokes and paragraph marks in red or blue. Four leaves bound in front; foliation, 207-236, added in red. Binding: brown morocco. Provenance: Hartmann Schedel (hand-painted shield on leaf a2 with Negro's head; ms. paragraph on endsheet (verso of leaf numbered 210); cf. D.C. Duniway, A study of the Nuremberg chronicle, in: Papers of the Bib. Society of America, v. 35 (1941), p. 21; Bibliotheca Regia Monacensis (ink-stamp).
- Balbi, Giovanni, d. 1298. Incipit summa que vocatur Catholicon edita a Fratre Iohanne de Ianua Ordinis Fratrum Predicatorum.[Strasbourg: Georg Husner, not after 30 June 1482], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1482 .B25 f; [788] p. (1st 2 p. and last 2 p. blank); 42 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 130 (IC.1932). Goff (rev.), B-24. GW 3186. Hain-Copinger, 2252. ISTC (RLIN), ib00024000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: Initial and elaborate floral border on [a2r] in red, blue, green and gold; initials in red or blue; initial strokes, paragraph marks and underscoring in red. Imperfect: 1st and last blank leaves lacking; initial removed from [D2]. Binding: blind-stamped leather over boards; remnants of clasps. Fore-edge title: Catholicon. Provenance: In floral border [a2r]: Ex Bibliotheca Sancta Barbara Brixina anno Domini MDCLXII; Ewald Flgel library (booklabel); Pastorius (inscription); Oswald Weigel ... Leipzig (bookseller's stamp); ms. marginalia.
- Euclid. Elementa geometria.[Venice]: Erhardus Ratdolt Augustensis impressor solertissimus Venetiijs impressit, anno salutis M.cccc.lxxxij octauis calen[darum] Iun[ii] [25 May 1482], Call No. Barchas Collection KA1482 .E88 F; [276] p. (1st and last 2 blank): woodcuts; 30 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 285 (IB.20513). GW 9428. Goff (rev.), E-113. Hain-Copinger 6693. Horblit, H.D. Grolier 100 science books, 27. ISTC (RLIN), ie00113000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Provenance: Wm. Crocker deposit (inscription); scant ms. marginalia on p. [2]-[3]. Rubrication: untouched. Binding: full dark blue morocco, gilt panels; upper and lower covers have blind-stamped panels bordered in gilt with arabesques and devices at corners; marbled endpapers; all edges gilt. Binder: Riviere Son (stamp). Binder's title: Euclid. Venetus 1482; in case, with title: Elementa geometrica.
- Higden, Ranulf, d. 1364. [A leaf from the Polychronicon] Grete thankynges, lawde, honoure we merytoryously ben bounde to yelde and offre vnto wryters of hystoryes whiche gretely haue prouffyted oure mortal lyf that shewe vnto the reders and herers by the ensamples of thynges passyd what thynge is to be desyred.[Westminster: William Caxton, after 2 July 1482], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1482 .H54; [2] p.; 23 cm.
  Text consists of end of chapter 23 and beginning of chapter 24 of book 6.
  References: Goff (rev.), H-267. Hain-Copinger 8659. ISTC ih00267000. STC 13438.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initial, heading, paragraph marks in red. Binding: in red folding portfolio. Spine title: Higden. Polychronicon. Provenance: Hansard Watt (bookplate); Kate Felton Elkins (bookplate); ms. marginalia in red.
- Persius. Auli Flacci Persii poetae Satyraru[m] opus.[Venice]: Per me magistru[m] Renaldu[m] de Nouimagio Theutonicu[m] Venetiis impressum, anno M.CCCC.LXXXII. me[n]sis Dece[m]bris die XXIIII [24 Dec. 1482], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1482 .P38 f; [44] p.; 31 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), P-345. Hain-Copinger, 12722. ISTC, ip00345000. "Bartholomeus Fontius Francisco Saxetto salutem": p. [42]-[43]. "Vita Persii": p. [43].